I'm speaking about compassion from an Islamic point of view,
Hablo de la compasión desde el punto de vista islámico,
and perhaps my faith is not very well thought of as being one that is grounded in compassion.
y tal vez mi fe no sea vista como una fe arraigada en la compasión.
The truth of the matter is otherwise.
La verdad es otra.
Our holy book, the Koran, consists of 114 chapters,
Nuestro libro sagrado, el Corán, consiste de 114 capítulos,
and each chapter begins with what we call the basmala,
y cada capítulo comienza con lo que llamamos la basmala,
the saying of "In the name of God, the all compassionate, the all merciful,"
decimos: en el nombre de Dios, el Clemente y Misericordioso
or, as Sir Richard Burton --
o, como Sir Richard Burton,
not the Richard Burton who was married to Elizabeth Taylor,
no el Richard Burton que fue esposo de Elizabeth Taylor,
but the Sir Richard Burton who lived a century before that and who was a worldwide traveler
sino Sir Richard Burton, quien vivió un siglo antes, viajó por todo el mundo
and translator of many works of literature --
y fue traductor de muchas obras literarias,
translates it. "In the name of God, the compassionating, the compassionate."
él lo traduce como: "en el nombre de Dios, Graciabilísimo, Misericordiosísimo".
And in a saying of the Koran, which to Muslims is God speaking to humanity, God says to his prophet Muhammad --
En un pasaje del Corán, que para los musulmanes es Dios que le habla a la Humanidad. Dios dice a su profeta Mahoma,
whom we believe to be the last of a series of prophets,
quien creemos fue el último de un linaje de profetas,
beginning with Adam, including Noah, including Moses, including Abraham,
comenzando con Adán, luego Noé, Moisés y Abrahán,
including Jesus Christ, and ending with Muhammad --
incluyendo Jesucristo, terminando con Mahoma
that, "We have not sent you, O Muhammad,
dijo: "No te enviamos, oh, Mahoma,
except as a 'rahmah,' except as a source of compassion to humanity."
excepto como raham, como fuente de compasión para la Humanidad".
For us human beings, and certainly for us as Muslims,
Para nosotros, como seres humanos, y como musulmanes,
whose mission, and whose purpose in following the path of the prophet
cuya misión y propósito es seguir la senda del profeta,
is to make ourselves as much like the prophet.
debemos llegar a ser como el profeta
And the prophet, in one of his sayings, said, "Adorn yourselves with the attributes of God."
y el profeta dijo: "Adórnense con los atributos divinos".
And because God Himself said that the primary attribute of his is compassion --
Porque Dios dijo que su principal atributo es la compasión,
in fact, the Koran says that "God decreed upon himself compassion,"
de hecho, el Corán dice: "Dios se autoimpuso la compasión",
or, "reigned himself in by compassion" -- therefore, our objective and our mission must be to be sources of compassion,
o "reinó sobre sí mediante la compasión". Por tanto, tenemos el objetivo y la misión de ser fuentes de compasión,
activators of compassion, actors of compassion
activadores de la compasión, actores de la compasión,
and speakers of compassion and doers of compassion.
voceros de la compasión, hacedores de la compasión.
That is all well and good,
Todo eso está bien,
but where do we go wrong,
pero ¿Dónde nos equivocamos,
and what is the source of the lack of compassion in the world?
y cuál es la causa de la falta de compasión en el mundo?
For the answer to this, we turn to our spiritual path.
Para hallar la respuesta, acudimos a nuestra senda espiritual.
In every religious tradition, there is the outer path and the inner path,
En cada tradición espiritual, existe una senda externa y una interna,
or the exoteric path and the esoteric path.
o la senda exotérica y la senda esotérica.
The esoteric path of Islam is more popularly known as Sufism, or "tasawwuf" in Arabic.
La senda esotérica del Islam se conoce como el sufismo, o tasawwuf en árabe.
And these doctors or these masters,
Y todos estos doctores o maestros,
these spiritual masters of the Sufi tradition,
estos maestros espirituales de la tradición sufí,
refer to teachings and examples of our prophet
se refieren a las enseñanzas y los ejemplos de nuestro profeta,
that teach us where the source of our problems lies.
que nos enseñan adónde está la fuente de nuestros problemas.
In one of the battles that the prophet waged, he told his followers, "We are returning from the lesser war
En una de las batallas donde luchó nuestro profeta, él dijo a sus seguidores: "Regresamos de una guerra menor
to the greater war, to the greater battle."
e iremos hacia una guerra mayor, la batalla mayor".
And they said, "Messenger of God, we are battle-weary.
Y ellos dijeron: "Mensajero de Dios, estamos cansados de la batalla.
How can we go to a greater battle?"
¿Cómo habríamos de ir a una batalla mayor?
He said, "That is the battle of the self, the battle of the ego."
Él dijo: "Esa es la batalla del ser, la batalla del ego".
The sources of human problems have to do with egotism, "I."
Las fuentes de los problemas humanos se relacionan con el egoismo, el Yo.
The famous Sufi master Rumi, who is very well known to most of you, has a story in which he talks of a man who goes to the house of a friend,
El famoso maestro sufí, Rumi, muy conocido por ustedes, cuenta una historia sobre un hombre que visita la casa de un amigo
and he knocks on the door,
toca la puerta,
and a voice answers, "Who's there?"
y una voz responde: "¿Quién es?"
"It's me," or, more grammatically correctly, "It is I,"
"Soy yo"
The voice says, "Go away."
La voz dice: "Vete".
After many years of training, of disciplining, of search and struggle, he comes back.
Después de muchos años de adiestramiento, disciplina y lucha, él regresa,
With much greater humility, he knocks again on the door.
y con mayor humildad, nuevamente toca la puerta.
The voice asks, "Who is there?"
La voz pregunta: "¿Quién es?"
He said, "It is you, O heartbreaker."
Él responde: "Eres tú, oh, inconmovible".
The door swings open, and the voice says,
La puerta se abre, y la voz dice:
"Come in, for there is no room in this house for two I's,"
"Entra, ya que no hay espacio en esta casa para dos "Yo",
-- two capital I's, not these eyes -- "for two egos."
2 yo (en inglés rima con eye), no 2 ojos (eyes), para 2 egos.
And Rumi's stories are metaphors for the spiritual path.
Las historias de Rumi son metáforas de la senda espiritual.
In the presence of God, there is no room for more than one "I,"
En presencia de Dios, no hay espacio para más de un Yo,
and that is the "I" of divinity.
y ése es el Yo de la divinidad.
In a teaching -- called a "hadith qudsi" in our tradition --
En una enseñanza llamada "hadith qudsi" en nuestra tradición,
God says that, "My servant," or "My creature, my human creature,
Dios dice: "Mi siervo", o "mi criatura", mi criatura humana
does not approach me by anything that is dearer to me
no se aproxima a mí por ningún medio más preciado
than what I have asked them to do."
que a través de aquéllo que le he pedido hacer".
And those of you who are employers know exactly what I mean.
Y los patronos saben bien lo que quiero decir.
You want your employees to do what you ask them to do,
Quieren que sus empleados hagan lo que pidan,
and if they've done that, then they can do extra.
y si lo hacen, pueden hacer aún más,
But don't ignore what you've asked them to do. "And," God says, "my servant continues to get nearer to me,
pero no ignoran lo que ustedes les pidieron hacer. Y Dios dice: "Mi siervo se acerca más a mí
by doing more of what I've asked them to do" --
al hacer más de lo que le he pedido".
extra credit, we might call it --
ganando puntos extra, podríamos decir,
"until I love him or love her.
"haciéndome amarlo.
And when I love my servant," God says,
Y cuando amo a mi siervo", dice Dios,
"I become the eyes by which he or she sees,
Me transformo en los ojos por los que él o ella ve,
the ears by which he or she listens, the hand by which he or she grasps,
los oídos por los que escucha, la mano con la que empuña,
and the foot by which he or she walks,
el pie con que camina,
and the heart by which he or she understands."
el corazón que le da entendimiento".
It is this merging of our self with divinity
Ésta es la fusión de nuestro ser con la divinidad,
that is the lesson and purpose of our spiritual path and all of our faith traditions.
la lección y el fin de nuestra senda espiritual, de todas nuestras tradiciones de fe.
Muslims regard Jesus as the master of Sufism,
Los musulmanes ven a Jesús como el maestro del sufismo,
the greatest prophet and messenger who came to emphasize the spiritual path. When he says, "I am the spirit, and I am the way,"
el más grande profeta y mensajero, que vino a resaltar la senda espiritual. Cuando él dice: "Yo soy el Espíritu, Yo soy el camino",
and when the prophet Muhammad said, "Whoever has seen me has seen God,"
cuando el profeta Mahoma dijo: "Quien me ha visto, ha visto a Dios",
it is because they became so much an instrument of God,
es porque se han convertido en un instrumento de Dios,
they became part of God's team --
son parte del hálito de Dios,
so that God's will was manifest through them, and they were not acting from their own selves and their own egos.
y así la voluntad de Dios se manifestó a través de ellos ya que no actuaban desde sí mismos y desde su ego.
Compassion on earth is given, it is in us.
La compasión terrenal nos es dada, ya está en nosotros.
All we have to do is to get our egos out of the way,
Todo lo que debemos hacer es retirar nuestros egos,
get our egotism out of the way.
deshacernos de nuestro egoismo.
I'm sure, probably all of you here, or certainly the very vast majority of you,
Estoy seguro de que todos ustedes, o la gran mayoría
have had what you might call a spiritual experience,
han tenido una experiencia espiritual,
a moment in your lives when, for a few seconds, a minute perhaps,
un momento de sus vidas en que, por unos segundos, tal vez un minuto,
the boundaries of your ego dissolved.
los límites del ego se disolvieron.
And at that minute, you felt at one with the universe --
Y durante ese minuto se sintieron uno con el Universo,
one with that jug of water, one with every human being,
uno con esa jarra de agua, uno con cada ser humano.
one with the Creator --
uno con el creador,
and you felt you were in the presence of power, of awe,
y se sintieron en presencia del poder, del asombro,
of the deepest love, the deepest sense of compassion and mercy that you have ever experienced in your lives.
del más profundo amor, la más profunda compasión y misericordia que hayan experimentado en sus vidas.
That is a moment which is a gift of God to us -- a gift when, for a moment, he lifts that boundary
Ese momento es un presente de Dios para nosotros, un obsequio en que, por un momento, él retira esa barrera
which makes us insist on "I, I, I, me, me, me," and instead, like the person in Rumi's story,
que nos hace insistir en Yo, Yo, Yo, y a cambio, como la persona en la historia de Rumi
we say, "Oh, this is all you. This is all you. And this is all us.
decimos: "Oh, todo esto eres tú". Todo esto eres tú. Y todo esto somos nosotros.
And us, and I, and us are all part of you.
Y nosotros, y yo, y todos nosotros somos parte tuya.
O, Creator! O, the Objective! The source of our being
Creador de todas las cosas, todos los fines, la fuente de nuestro ser,
and the end of our journey,
y el final de nuestra travesía.
you are also the breaker of our hearts.
También eres quien rompe nuestros corazones.
You are the one whom we should all be towards, for whose purpose we live,
Eres aquél a quien debemos dirigirnos, aquél por quien vivimos,
and for whose purpose we shall die,
y aquél por quien habremos de morir,
and for whose purpose we shall be resurrected again
y por quien habremos de resucitar
to account to God to what extent we have been compassionate beings."
para justificar ante Dios cuán compasivos hemos sido.
Our message today, and our purpose today,
Hoy nuestro mensaje y propósito,
and those of you who are here today,
y quienes están hoy aquí,
and the purpose of this charter of compassion, is to remind.
y el propósito de este capítulo de compasión, es recordar.
For the Koran always urges us to remember, to remind each other,
Y es que el Corán siempre nos urge recordar, que nos recordemos,
because the knowledge of truth is within every human being. We know it all.
porque el conocimiento de la verdad está en cada ser humano. Sabemos todo.
We have access to it all.
Tenemos acceso a todo.
Jung may have called it "the subconscious."
Jung lo llamó el inconsciente.
Through our subconscious, in your dreams --
A través de nuestro inconsciente, en nuestros sueños,
the Koran calls our state of sleep "the lesser death,"
lo que el Corán llama, estar durmiendo, la muerte menor,
"the temporary death" --
la muerte temporal.
in our state of sleep we have dreams, we have visions, we travel even outside of our bodies, for many of us,
Cuando dormimos, soñamos, tenemos visiones, incluso muchos viajamos fuera de nuestros cuerpos,
and we see wonderful things.
y vemos cosas maravillosas.
We travel beyond the limitations of space as we know it,
Viajamos más allá de las limitaciones del espacio, tal como lo conocemos,
and beyond the limitations of time as we know it.
y más allá de las limitaciones del tiempo, tal como lo conocemos.
But all this is for us to glorify the name of the creator
Pero todo esto es para glorificar el nombre del creador
whose primary name is the compassionating, the compassionate.
cuyo nombre primordial es el Clemente, el Compasivo.
God, Bokh, whatever name you want to call him with, Allah, Ram, Om,
Dios, Bokh, como deseen llamarlo, Alá, Ram, Om,
whatever the name might be through which you name
sea cual fuere el nombre que usen para denotar
or access the presence of divinity,
o llegar a la presencia de la divinidad,
it is the locus of absolute being,
es el locus del ser absoluto,
absolute love and mercy and compassion,
amor, piedad y compasión absolutos,
and absolute knowledge and wisdom,
conocimiento y sabiduría absolutos,
what Hindus call "satchidananda."
lo que los hindúes llaman satchidananda.
The language differs,
El lenguaje puede cambiar,
but the objective is the same.
pero el objetivo es el mismo.
Rumi has another story
Hay otra historia de Rumi
about three men, a Turk, an Arab and --
de tres personajes: un turco, un árabe,
and I forget the third person, but for my sake, it could be a Malay. One is asking for angur -- one is, say, an Englishman --
y olvido el tercero, pero podría ser un malayo. Uno pide angour, el otro es, digamos, un británico,
one is asking for eneb, and one is asking for grapes.
uno pide eneb, y el otro pide uvas.
And they have a fight and an argument because
Y pelean y discuten porque
-- "I want grapes." "I want eneb. "I want angur." --
Yo quiero uvas, yo quiero eneb, yo quiero angour,
not knowing that the word that they're using
sin saber que la palabra que usan
refers to the same reality in different languages.
se refiere a la misma realidad en diferentes idiomas.
There's only one absolute reality by definition,
Sólo hay una realidad absoluta por definición,
one absolute being by definition, because absolute is, by definition, single,
un solo ser absoluto por definición, porque lo absoluto es, por definición, único,
and absolute and singular.
absoluto y singular.
There's this absolute concentration of being,
Hay una concentración absoluta del ser,
the absolute concentration of consciousness,
la absoluta concentración de la conciencia,
awareness, an absolute locus of compassion and love
la cognición, un locus absoluto de compasión y amor
that defines the primary attributes of divinity.
que define los atributos divinos primordiales.
And these should also be
Y ésos también deben ser
the primary attributes of what it means to be human.
los principales atributos de lo que significa la humanidad.
For what defines humanity, perhaps biologically, is our physiology,
Ya que lo que define a humanidad, tal vez de manera biológica, es nuestra fisiología,
but God defines humanity by our spirituality, by our nature.
pero Dios define a la humanidad por nuestra espiritualidad y naturaleza.
And the Koran says, He speaks to the angels and says,
El Corán dice, él habló a los ángeles y dijo:
"When I have finished the formation of Adam from clay,
"Cuando termine de formar a Adán con arcilla,
and breathed into him of my spirit,
e insufle en él mi espíritu,
then, fall in prostration to him."
entonces póstrense ante él".
The angels prostrate, not before the human body,
Los ángeles se postraron, no ante el cuerpo humano,
but before the human soul.
sino ante el alma humana.
Why? Because the soul, the human soul,
¿Por qué? Porque el alma, el alma humana,
embodies a piece of the divine breath,
encarna parte del hálito divino,
a piece of the divine soul.
parte del alma divina.
This is also expressed in biblical vocabulary
Esto también se expresa en el vocabulario bíblico
when we are taught that we were created in the divine image.
cuando nos enseñan que fuimos creados en semenjanza a la imagen divina.
What is the imagery of God?
¿Cuál es la imaginería de Dios?
The imagery of God is absolute being,
La imaginería de Dios es el ser absoluto,
absolute awareness and knowledge and wisdom
cognición, conocimiento y sabiduría absolutos,
and absolute compassion and love.
amor y compasión absolutos.
And therefore, for us to be human --
Entonces, para que seamos humanos,
in the greatest sense of what it means to be human,
en el más alto sentido de lo que significa ser humano,
in the most joyful sense of what it means to be human --
en el más gozoso sentido de lo que significa ser humano,
means that we too have to be proper stewards
quiere decir que también nosotros debemos ser facilitadores
of the breath of divinity within us,
del hálito divino que yace en nosotros,
and seek to perfect within ourselves the attribute of being, of being alive, of beingness;
y buscar perfeccionar en nosotros el atributo del ser, de estar vivos, de nuestra condición de ser,
the attribute of wisdom, of consciousness, of awareness;
el atributo de la sabiduría, consciencia, cognición,
and the attribute of being compassionate and loving beings.
y el atributo de ser seres compasivos y amorosos.
This is what I understand from my faith tradition,
Esto es lo que entiendo de la tradición de mi fe,
and this is what I understand from my studies of other faith traditions,
y esto es lo que entiendo de mis estudios de otras tradiciones de fe,
and this is the common platform on which we must all stand,
ésta es la plataforma común que todos debemos pisar,
and when we stand on this platform as such,
y cuando pisemos esta plataforma
I am convinced that we can make a wonderful world.
estoy convencido de que podremos crear un mundo maravilloso.
And I believe, personally, that we're on the verge
Y creo, personalmente, que estamos cerca,
and that, with the presence and help of people like you here,
y con la presencia y ayuda de personas como ustedes,
we can bring about the prophecy of Isaiah.
podemos hacer realidad la profecía de Isaías.
For he foretold of a period
Él predijo una era
when people shall transform their swords into plowshares
en la que la gente transformará sus espadas en arados
and will not learn war or make war anymore.
y no aprenderán la guerra, y ya no librarán la guerra.
We have reached a stage in human history that we have no option: we must, we must lower our egos,
Hemos llegado a una etapa de la historia humana donde no hay opción. Debemos aplacar nuestros egos,
control our egos -- whether it is individual ego, personal ego,
controlar nuestros egos, sea el ego individual, personal,
family ego, national ego -- and let all be for the glorification of the one.
el ego familiar, el ego nacional, y que todo sea por glorificar el uno.
Thank you, and God bless you.
Gracias, y que Dios los bendiga.
(Applause)
(Aplausos)